<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands alarm from the north, vvherein the affaires of Scotland are represented, with the ominous aspect they have to England, to awaken all interests to consider of the nearest conjunction among themselves against the common enemie, who appears in a new disguize, yet as destructive as ever to our lawes, liberties, and priviledges.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E434_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205279</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864695</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864695</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83946)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116927)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 68:E434[24])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands alarm from the north, vvherein the affaires of Scotland are represented, with the ominous aspect they have to England, to awaken all interests to consider of the nearest conjunction among themselves against the common enemie, who appears in a new disguize, yet as destructive as ever to our lawes, liberties, and priviledges.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert White,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March" (crossed out); "Aprill 4th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116927:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Englands Alarm FROM THE NORTH, VVherein the affaires of <hi>Scotland</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, with the ominous aſpect they have to <hi>England,</hi> to awaken all intereſts to conſider of the neareſt conjunction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves againſt the common Enemie, who appears in a new diſguize, yet as deſtructive as ever to our Lawes, Liberties, and Priviledges.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Reſpublica incolumis, &amp; privatas res facile ſalvas praeſtat, publica perdendo, tua nequicquam ſerves.</hi>
               <bibl> Liv. lib. 26.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert White</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116927:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116927:2"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS Alarm from the NORTH.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere it not that ſome ſpeciall judgement from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven lies on the moſt of this Nation for our formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and unthankfulneſſe, it were impoſſible to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that we ſhould be ſo ignorant and inſenſible of the deſignes which are yet upon us; he which caſts his eyes back with any obſervation of ſeven yeares procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, cannot but have ſeene ſuch a contexture of plots, and ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems, to ruine this Kingdome, as hath not beene before in ſuch a ſpace of time; and had we been good husbands of our experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, we might have both foreſeen, and prevented many miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs which are like to come upon us. But we may ſadly lament, inſtead of obſerving the publike contrivances of our enemies, we have cloſed in with many of them, and are like to ingage again on the ſame deſigne (if God prevent it not.) God hath done enough to open our eyes, and Providence hath diſcovered that, as at noon day, which lay hid, and was for a long time carried on by ſecret and only ſuſpicious ſteps; and that we might have a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their intentions, our enemies have writ them in bloud, and we have the undeniable prints of their malice on our bodies, eſtates and liberties, yea our Religion and conſciences. But this hath been our miſery, though we have felt the paine, yet we have not looked into the deſigne, nor eyed the ſecret and inviſible paths and formes theſe men have walked in. We ſhould have had no neede of any paper diſcoveries if we had carefully obſerved the reall and manifeſt practiſes of theſe men but within theſe few yeares. But becauſe I may not ſpeake at randome, and all that can be done is little enough to make men ſenſible of their own good, I cannot but tell you that you are yet on the ſands, and have need now if ever to open your <hi>Engliſh</hi> eyes, and ſtand upon your guard,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116927:3"/> for there are yet who ſeeke to make a prey of the richeſt and ſweeteſt of your injoyments. We have very loud Alarmes from the North which beſpeak ſtrange things, I ſhall give you what I know, and many honeſt and wiſe men juſtly feare, that the old Engineers are ſtill at work to undermine (though in a more cloſe and hanſome way) the very foundation of our peace and liberties. When we look to heaven, we may well feare the quarrell is not ended there, our unfruitfulneſſe hath been ſo great under the late happy diſpenſations of the Almighty to us; but that ſtill ſome ſharper arrowes, and bitterer pills are providing for us; if we look to men we may promiſe our ſelves that all advantages ſhall be taken againſt us, and indeed many clouds farre above the bigneſſe of a mans hand ariſe in the North, the vapours of which have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended partly from the South, and are yet increaſing as if they would fill the whole heavens, which many wiſe men upon great reaſons think will not diſtill in moiſt and ſpring-like ſhowers, but in bloud and miſerie, on this poor Nation, if the Lord for his own name ſake be not very mercifull. And that you may the better prognoſticate, and be awakened, it will not be amiſſe to lead you back unto the conſideration of the old deſigne, and how its like now to be carried on under another habit with as great diligence as ever, and if poſſible you may be quickned up to a ſerious and deepe apprehenſiou of what miſchiefes do await you.</p>
            <p>Two great intereſts have been for a long time apparently driven on with a high hand in theſe three Kingdomes, the Kings, and the Clergies, the one for Prerogative, the other for Poperie, the one to bring us nigher <hi>Turkie,</hi> the other nigher <hi>Rome;</hi> and though they ſeeme to be different, yet they have both interwoven intereſts for the mutuall ſtrengthening of each other, and profeſſe one common cauſe; they well knowing that the beſt way to inſlave our bodies, was firſt to ingage our conſciences, and the way to make our conſciences ſtoope, was to tyranniſe over our bodies. This deſigne was carried on ſecretly for a long wile, untill at laſt through the oppoſition of this Parliament, it broke out into a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116927:3"/> bloudy and cruell warre, which was not managed by children or fooles, but with the greateſt policie and ſtrength, as the wifeſt heads could conjecture; but after many and tedious overtures, and bloudy battels, God appeared againſt them, by a poor and deſpiſed new Modell, and we obtained a full and abſolute conqueſt over them, ſo that now all honeſt hearts ſeemed to be at reſt, &amp; to have ſate downe, and have eaten the fruits of ſuch a glorious mercy.</p>
            <p>But though the warre be done, the deſigne is not done, other wayes are eſſayed to give opportunitie to our old adverſaries; the Covenant is brought in, by the now ruling malignant partie in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as a bait to catch honeſt men, the Presbyteriall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be made the next ground of a quarrel, as if that was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to effect what Epiſcopacie could not. A new kinde of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants ariſe in both Kingdomes, which are of two ſorts; ſome great Malignants formerly, and actually in armes, to ſave their Compoſitions take the Covenant, are againe admitted to our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes; and others who, though not in armes, yet ever were of the Kings ſide, ſtrike in with honeſt men whom they finde zealous for the Presbyteriall Government, preſſe them to the purſuing of uniformitie to the crying downe the Armie; whence diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, new names are found out to diſtinguiſh and divide, that ſome might reigne. Thoſe which were not fully complying with their ends are called Independents, and Sectaries, and repreſented as the only plagues of the Kingdoms, &amp; incompatible with the good of either nation; the common enemie doth not ſtirre all this while, as being under the laſh, and knowing that the very mention of them would be odious, the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners muſt be imployed to ply the Citizens with Declarations, to get into the hearts of the Miniſters, and to ingage them, profeſſe only their deſires for the Church, the puritie and uniformitie of it; and that this may be the more effectuall, Remonſtrances muſt be Printed againſt the Parliament and their proceedings, and that by the <hi>Scots</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, men publickly intruſted with the affaires of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116927:4"/> wherein the Parliament muſt be taxed for breach of Covenant, for neglect of the Church; and that you may ſee the bottome of the buſineſſe, the comming of the King to <hi>London</hi> is thought fit as the only medium, and a perſonall Treatie preſt with ſo much violence, as if they meant to bring him by the force of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, againſt the Sence of both Houſes of Parliament; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners muſt go viſit the King in the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> and there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt the Parliaments Propoſitions (though only propoſing the very ſubſtance of what we fought for) and for what private conferences they had with his Majeſtie, though we know not the words, we may eaſily underſtand the ſence by their carriages ſince, and what is now doing in <hi>Scotland.</hi> How ſtrangely by theſe tranſactions we are divided, and what hopes and expectations are in our common enemies we may feele before we are aware. And that ſome ingagement hath been made between ſome of the Grandees of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the King, is more then probable, if there were no more preſumption of it then that ſecret and clandeſtine proceeding of the Comiſſioners in the Iſle of <hi>Wight.</hi> But when we do conſider of the modell of the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and how it is framed, and patcht with Malignants, and how they cry up the Kings Intereſt againſt the honeſt party in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> we may well ſuſpect that we ſhall want nothing of the ſame deſigne, but the name, and the place from whence it is viſibly to be acted. And theſe things are not bug-beares (though falſe Alarms are ſometimes uſefull) ſome of their own godly Miniſters, the laſt Faſt, did publiquely declare the great plottings and contrivings in the Parliament to ingage againſt the honeſt party, and did even ſo point out the Agents (who were no mean ones) that the ſame night a challenge was ſent from the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, Lord <hi>Craford Lindſey,</hi> to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Argyle,</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Marqueſſe had preſt them to ſpeak what they did, the Lord <hi>Lindſey</hi> being one pointed out in the deſigne. And that you may yet be certaine of the ſtrenuous indeavours of theſe men
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116927:4"/> to effect this work, you have it declared by the generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in their late Declaration. And beſides all this that we may have demonſtration upon demonſtration, the continuall concourſe of Cavaliers from all parts, eſpecially of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with the cold entertainment of our Commiſſioners, and the great neglect and contempt of Mr. <hi>Marſhall</hi> for but endeavouring a peace between the Army and the City, ſpeak loud enough, that any one who is not loſt in the ſame deſigne cannot but be ſenſible of. And if it be not yet time for us to awake and conſider what we are do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we may feele before we fear our danger; the great incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of this deſigne is our diviſions, upon which ſtock they graffe all their hopes. <hi>O Populi ad ſervitutem non ad libertatem nati?</hi> Is there not a ſpark of true gallantry, and of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Spirits, yet within you? Have the ſound of Drums and Trumpets made you quite deafe, and ſlavery and faction quite put out your eyes? Is there any Intereſt like to the Publique? Is it not now high time to unite, when others mean to unite againſt you? Whom do you gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie but your common enemy? and ſhall your diviſions give life againe to the dying hopes of thoſe ſonnes of violence? Had it not been better you had peaceably laid down your necks at firſt, then to have given ground for ſuch cruell revenge? I would theſe were but paſſionate expreſſions, and that we had not too much ground to inculcate them in every <hi>Engliſh</hi> heart. But we muſt take off a diſguiſe, or elſe we ſhall but loſe our labour, and ſpeak to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged men. There are many glorious, and faire pretences, which are urged and made the ground of a new quarrell, though the truth is, they are but made the veile and varniſh of the old cauſe: the ſetting up the Covenant, and Presbytery, contrary to Sectaries and Schiſmatickes. But what ever is pretended, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe is intended, and if it be intended firſt, I am ſure it will be executed laſt; after they have ſerved their own ends upon <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> they may perchance ſerve that. But that honeſt and well meaning men may ſee how they are cheated, and that there can
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116927:5"/> be no ſuch quarrell with <hi>England</hi> either for the Covenant, or for Presbyteriall Government, let it be conſidered, firſt that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament have according to the advice of the Aſſembly ſtabliſhed it, and have declared their intentions concerning it, that they have and will ſet it up as the Government of the Kingdome, and have given it the great preeminence of and above all others by its publick ſtamp of Authority and maintenance, ſo that there can be no pretence for that, except they will quarrell about an unlimited power, which the Parliament cannot with ſafety give them, which can be offenſive to none but thoſe who hold that Principle, <hi>Non dominari inſtar ſervitatis eſt,</hi> who think they are ſlaves except they be rulers. But ſuppoſe Presbytery ſhould not be ſet up, yet doth it deſerve the hazard of all the blood, and liberties of <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, to purchaſe its eſtabliſhment, which is ſo new to us, and of which we have ſuch little experience, yea whoſe name is not in the Covenant, but as it referres to <hi>Scotland,</hi> to whoſe modell we are not to be tide, but as we judge it to be according to the word of God? Muſt <hi>Scotland</hi> have needs <hi>Bellum Presbyteriale</hi> with us, as the <hi>Biſhops</hi> had <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale</hi> with them? can nothing but warre make up our difference? Let men but remember the event of the Biſhops warre, and then they will have little heart to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage Nations for an unexperienced Church government. Hath Presbytery been indeared to us for ſo many hundred years, and hath it left ſuch ſure and happy pledges of its divine deſcent in the pureſt diſtillations of holineſſe, A peace, that its impoſſible for us to keep God and our liberties together without it? if ſo, we ſhould be glad to venture the choiſeſt of our outward accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to obtain it; and let me adde this, That when Presbytery ſhall give us good teſtimony of her benigneſſe to <hi>England,</hi> as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy hath of her malignity, we ſhall be able to plead more for her. But its too common for men of no religion to beginne their moſt miſchievous practiſes with that name. I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how theſe men can be ſo true to that government, which ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116927:5"/> often calls them to the ſtoole of repentance: But to be ſerious, that there is no ſuch matter in hand, as either Covenant, or Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Government, but purely the Kings Intereſt, Let us but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider firſt that the greateſt Malignants which have been in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> are now taken into the very boſome of their Parliament, as the Marqueſſe <hi>Huntly,</hi> the Lord <hi>Traquaire,</hi> with many others who have been the greateſt Incendiaries of that Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Who are the great Agents in this buſineſſe, and do carry the ſway in this deſigne, but men who have ever been oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite unto the Covenant, as Mr. <hi>George Gelleſpy</hi> ſpake openly in the Pulpit at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> that there are now got up into the greateſt places, to ſit at the helme, men of ſtrange faces, who were never known to appeare for the cauſe of the Covenant, but have ever oppoſed Reformation to the utmoſt of their power; and that you may ghueſſe by the leaders which way the conduct is like to be, you may take their names with their ſhort characters too well known of them. The firſt and great one who ſteeres moſt inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly this Affayre is Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> one who loves the Crowne better then the King, and yet its thought he acts out of a different and peculiar end; the Lord <hi>Traquaire,</hi> a man formerly excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated both out of Church and State, but now the great Favourite of this Faction; the Lord <hi>Lanericke,</hi> a younger Brother to the Duke, who can no more live without the Beams of Majeſty, then the plant without the Sun, who was ſo deare to the King, as he made him his Secretary at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> to ſupply the place of the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> who can no way exceed him in policy and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy; the Lord <hi>Calender,</hi> who hath been a Black-bander, &amp; as ſecretly diſaffected to the Covenant as any of the reſt, only ingaged by his Leiutenant-Generall-Ship, and ſome particular diſcontents to <hi>Montroſſe.</hi> Its well known how often he hath been at Court within theſe few monthes; I might adde many more. But that you may know <hi>ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pede Herculem.</hi> Can any wiſe man imagine that theſe men ſhould now begin to ingage on the intereſt of the Covenant,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116927:6"/> which they never owned before with any affection, and which is ſo diametrically oppoſite to their own private ingagements: But how ever, the Covenant muſt bear the name! or again, can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that thoſe who ſhall ſtand for the King, &amp; joyn with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy to ſet Him in His Throne who refuſeth to take the Covenant, or give any ſatisfaction to what is contained in it (but only concerning his own Perſon) will ever maintain the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it ſelfe?</p>
            <p>But let it be granted that there was a reall violation of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in ſome particulars, and an ingagement ſhould be for that cauſe as the principle: yet it cannot be conceived, that the taking in of the common enemy to the quarrell, as Aſſiſtants, will ever manage ſuch an intention with any probable ſucceſſe, but it will rather endanger the whole cauſe, by putting weapons into their hands who aime at the ruine both of the cauſe and Covenant. Ye we know by ſad experience many a good end hath been ſoon left, or at leaſt miſtaken in the multitude and hurry of Affaires, and thoſe we have put much confidence in, have found it very eaſy to diſpenſe with their principles, to further their particular and private occaſions. We began well in <hi>England,</hi> and did ſet out ſo fairly, as honeſt, and plain dealing men thought every thing would be carried on uniformly, in effecting one common end. But <hi>Proteus</hi> never made ſo many faces and appearances, as there hath been changes and alterations in our Affaires. Let us now therefore be wiſe to know the meaning of pretences and principles, and not to be terrified from looking after our own good with the name Covenant, though ſpoken by the <hi>Scots</hi> themſelves with never ſo much zeal, and proteſtations, remembring how you have been formerly deceived into a miſerable warre by the Name King, and Common-Prayer Book. Religion is a bleſſed, and happy mercy, without which no Nations are ſecure; but when it comes in the hands of <hi>Politicians,</hi> &amp; to be made father to their deſignes, you muſt only look upon it as in their glaſſe, and you are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116927:6"/> to have it repreſented in another forme then its own. The Hiſtorian ſaid of old, <hi>Specie pietatis in ambitionem delabuntur;</hi> and its true now, men make Religion but the footſtoole of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular advancement; they make deſignes for their own advantage, and then intitle Gods name to it, that it may be the leſſe ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and ingage mens conſciences in it the more freely.</p>
            <p>But that they may not want a ſufficient vizard for their own ends, they tell us of the increaſing of Sectaries and Schiſmaticks, which is both dangerous to the Covenant and State, and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intends to tolerate them, againſt whom they cannot but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage by the Solemne league and Covenant; this is yet a fairer pretence, and ſeemes to be practicall, either to good, or ruine; but if it be well weighed, we may ſee a great fallacie whereby we may be eaſily deceived. The truth is, they have given us names, and will make it a ground of quarrell with us for being call'd by them; the moſt of theſe they call Sectaries are honeſt men, who ventured their lives in this Cauſe, and have been and are ſtill faithfull to the State, and if there be any difference its in ſome leſſer points of judgement, which yet they manage very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly and peaceably, and the wiſeſt men can hardly determine the things themſelves. Thus ſtrange &amp; formidable names are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to honeſt men, that they may be thought to be ſome ſtrange and deſperate creatures not fit to live in this world. But I hope <hi>Engliſh</hi> men will know how to call every faithfull man by his right name ſhortly. I would faine know whether there be any Sect or Schiſme now, or hath ever been known to be, like the Sect of the Malignants, which yet the <hi>Scots</hi> do not only tolerate, but intend to make uſe of to ſuppreſſe the Sects and Schiſmes in <hi>England:</hi> Will any man be ſo mad to hazard his bloud and eſtate to puniſh the ſecred erronious ſpeculations of another mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? or will the ſuppreſſion of them (take them in the worſt ſence) countervaile the coſt and charges, and the hazards that muſt be run to effect it? or can the <hi>Scots</hi> promiſe when theſe are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116927:7"/> ſuppreſt, we ſhall have no more Sects? nay, can they free us from worſe in the Church, and State? the truth is, when they have ſuppreſt them, they muſt thinke of dividing among themſelves, for intereſts make Sects, &amp; men will create intereſts as faſt as they ſee exigencies. When the <hi>Scots</hi> have got the art to beat all mens braines to one noddle, and all mens principles and ends to one intereſt, we may happily have ſome hopes of being free of Sects, in the meane while, though an eye muſt be over them, and thoſe ſuppreſt which are abſolutely deſtructive to the State, yet a wary indulgence muſt be afforded to ſome, leſt we make more Sects, by perſecution of them, then before. We never had ſo many Sects untill this warre, nor never ſuch names to divide them before the <hi>Scots</hi> were pleaſed to baptize them ſo, and we may feare on juſt grounds a multiplication of other kind of Sects, if ever a new war ſhould be promoted; for though the ingagement be one at firſt, yet the ends are different in the proſecution. By this time I doubt not but you may ſee into the bottome of that pretence as of the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, looke about you, a warre is threatned againſt you, great talks there are at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> of the breach of Covenant, of vindicating the honour of the King; you are fore-warned, be fore-armed; you have been ſorely whipt for your former ſtupiditie, let experience teach you wiſdome, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member names of things will never effect ends. You have fought againſt the King and his partie for your liberties, never give them away to another nation for nothing; things are now in a hopefull way of ſettlement, Peace begins to ſpring over all our injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, let us not ſuffer a <hi>Scots</hi> blaſt to nip our hopes in the bud. God knowes when ever we ſhall be ſo faire for libertie and peace, if we begin a new broil; the name of a warre ſhould now be as odious to all honeſt men, as the name of peace hath been, and is, to the ſonnes of violence. Many diſcontents are among you, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diviſions, make them up, leſt others diſcontent you more. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116927:7"/> are not eaſily foreſeen in hazardous &amp; difficult tranſactions, improve the preſent mercies you injoy, and pray for more, but take heed of making them leſſe by fomenting ſuch new differences among friends. Let us all lay to heart the danger of a new warre, the hazard of all that ever we have gained, the uncertaintie of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting the beſt pretences by ſuch a courſe. It can never enter into the heart of any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man except he hath been bred in the Highlands among the <hi>Redſhanks)</hi> that the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould ingage for a warre in <hi>England</hi> purely to preſerve our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and ſet up our liberties, or that they ſhould be more ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of our condition then the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> whom the whole Kingdome have intruſted, and of whoſe faithfulneſſe we have experience ſufficient, though an abſolute perfection is not to be expected from men on earth, and allowance muſt be given to men for failings, eſpecially who are imployed in multitude of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and who go through varietie of temptations Though we acknowledge <hi>Scotland</hi> a good neighbour, yet we have formerly thought that providence had well ordered it that the river <hi>Tweede</hi> ſhould run between us; and I cannot think him an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man that ſhall deſire any more bridges then <hi>Barwick</hi> to be made over it; for holding a brotherly correſpondence with us, we have not wanted grounds of ſuſpition that ſme thing more is deſired by them then a bare keeping up the Union. Wiſe men obſerve how they have of late pryed into our liberties, made many incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on our intereſts, ſeemed to challenge a part in the beſt and richeſt jewels of this State, affronted our Parliament to their faces, and that when they have had no army in <hi>England.</hi> Such forward eſſayes portend only want of power to effect it, which they may do in due time, if providence and our care prevent it not. Its not unknown how it was once pleaded hard at a Conference, that the name of great <hi>Brittaine</hi> might comprehend us all, and to leave out the diſtinct names of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> knowing that would be a handſome way to get an oneneſſe in power &amp; intereſt.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116927:8"/> And at another time it was preſt hard in both Houſes, and preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their Papers, that the foure Northern counties might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to them for the payment of their army, knowing that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion was eleven points of the Law, and a faire ſtep to a proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And all this propounded when they came in called by our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament purely on the intereſt of both Kingdoms equally in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But if ever they ſhould now come in let the pretence be as glorious as it will) you can expect nothing but a tranſplantation of many generations of them, into the beſt and fatteſt places of this Kingdome. <hi>England</hi> is too great a remptation for ſouldiers who have no other ends to ſerve but their own bellies. Put beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers on horſeback (pardon the compariſon) you know how they will ride. But a hint of theſe things may ſuffice, except we are willing to ſell our birth-right for a meſſe of pottage. The reſult of all ſhould be an earneſt endeavour of all the honeſt party in both King doms to unite, and accommodate among themſelves, waving the punctilio's of private difference, and fixing their eye on the deſignes of the common enemy, in the cloſe, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand tranſactions of them.</p>
            <p>And before I conclude, I think it will not be amiſſe to ſpend a few words on each intereſt, and that, if poſſible, we may be a wakened to a happy compliance againſt all our enemies. And becauſe our Brethren of <hi>Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> are now moſt in ſight, I cannot chooſe but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with them, &amp; give them this faithfull advice, as an honeſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanter, and true <hi>Engliſh</hi> man. (Brethren) we thank you for your brotherly aſſiſtance, we ſhall labour to requite you with the ſame, as we have opportunity, you were never ſo nigh <hi>England</hi> as now you are, the next breach will make us at a greater diſtance then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we were: he that makes the firſt breach, muſt expect the firſt ruine; we have mutually ingaged together againſt the common enemy, let us not now ingage with them againſt one another; let it never be ſaid that you had made a Covenant with us to put out our eyes; let not the dying hopes of our and your enemies be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116927:8"/> by you; give not occaſion to them to have one caſt more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt both Kingdoms. You have had ſufficient experience of Royall promiſes, and what the Kings ingagements have been to you; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cavaliers are the firſt born of his heart, and will be moſt reſpected becauſe of their firſt free and voluntary ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with him, and they hate your Covenant, and your Nation, more then any people in the world. When you have ſet up the King, you will give him leave to remember his old quarrell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you. Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gallants will never endure to ſee the beſt of you ſit down at the right hand of the Royall Majeſtie, you had better keep your eſteem you have with the Parliament, and the honeſt party in <hi>England,</hi> and give us time and peace to pay our debts, then crack your credit with every party. We ſhall call againſt you to the moſt High God for revenge of the greateſt treachery that ever was known, if you now joyn with our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy to undo this poor Nation. Do not verify that old character given you in all Hiſtories and Nations where your name is mentioned, that you are called <hi>Perſidi.</hi> Know this for certain, Though many in <hi>England</hi> would be glad to ſee things changed, yet they will never endure to ſee you rule Take heed that while you think to come into <hi>England,</hi> God doth not raiſe up a ſecond <hi>Montroſſe</hi> to ruine <hi>Scotland.</hi> Neither are we ſo low in <hi>England,</hi> but we can reſent your favours or frowns, and you will never make wiſe men believe, pretend Conſcience or Covenant, but your next coming muſt be to judgement, to part and divide our ſpoil among your poor deſpiſed Gentry and ſouldiers and though we have of late degenerated much from our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobleneſſe, and Gallantry, yet there is a veine of good blood that yet runs in ſome honeſt hearts, which will be prodigally ſpent upon ſuch treacherous underminers of our Liberties. But we have better thoughts of the honeſt party in <hi>Scotland,</hi> then that ever ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne ſhould come into their hearts, or get the leaſt countenance from them.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:116927:9"/>
            <p>It would be farre better, and more agreeing with our Covenant, that we ſhould come in to help you againſt that malignant Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which growes prevalent among you, then that you ſhould help them againſt your friends; and there need not to be any feare of our ſouldiers unwillingneſſe to come back again to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> though we muſt tell you plainly, you muſt give us leave to feare that if ever your ſouldiers come into us, we ſhall never get them out without blowes. If you will not further, do not envy our peace, you ſhall enjoy ſome of the fruits of it as well as we, make much of ſuch friends while you have them. The next whom I would addreſſe a few lines unto, are the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> (but I am loth to call names) who have been too far ingaged by the faire and ſmooth pretences of the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners: yet they are <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, and I have more hopes to prevaile on them to look about them. Though your judgements be not much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the <hi>Scots,</hi> yet your intereſts are. Let not the zeale of the Covenant eat out your love to the being of the Common-wealth. Settle not the foundation of Presbyterie in Chriſtian blood. Let the beams of truth ſhine abroad from you to diſpell and deſtroy errors. Call not for fire from Heaven, eſpecially not from <hi>Scotland,</hi> againſt your Brethren. The ſweetneſſe of your Spirits, the Rayes of Chriſts glory which ſhine from your doctrine, will do more to deſtroy the Kingdome of the Devill ſet up in the judgement of men, then all the ſwords and cannons in the world. Can you think that the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Cavaliers will ſettle an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterie? will your ſetting up the King, ſet up your Government? no, no, Epiſcopacy is too great a darling of the Kings, and his party, for them to give away its Crown to you. Souldiers will well minde Religion when once they get power; when they have ſerved your ends, you muſt ſerve theirs. Be content with what you have, let not the world ſee you aim purely at Domination, they will then ſoon conclude you are not <hi>Iure divino.</hi> Presbyterie may well give in ſome thing to an accommodation, as well as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116927:9"/> you have reaped the firſt fruits, yea the Harveſt of what we have yet ſown, though with many teares; you may well give leave to others of your Brethren to gather the gleanings of Peace and Liberty, ſince they have fought, and hazzarded their lives with you for the whole; you have the broad Seal for what you do, the publick ſtamp of the State, the ingagements of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for your maintenance, you may well give leave that a ſquint eye ſhould be caſt on other honeſt hearts, who deſire but to ſerve Chriſt according to that light they have; none ſeeks to be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors with you in your injoyments, or envies your priviledges, only deſire to ſit quietly down by you, ſerving of God with you, though not in the ſame externall forme. Will the moſt exacteſt externall Uniformity, if obtained by force, amount to the loſſe of innocent blood, and the oppreſſion and perſecution of any poor Saints? Remember what was the ruine of Epiſcopacy, but the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidneſſe of preſſing Conformity; let Pres byterie take heed ſhe come not to the ſame end by over-forcing an outward Uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And howere you may now think, the deſign is as much againſt the honeſt Presbyterians, as Independents; and though now we divide, we ſhall then be but one in the miſery, if ever through our own diviſions God ſhould let ſuch a device take effect. But they cannot be ignorant of theſe affaires; if they be, and are blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Scots miſt, I ſhall only wiſh they may have time enough to repent, when they ſhall feel the miſchiefs of ſuch an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</p>
            <p>And before I go further, I cannot paſſe by the City of' <hi>London,</hi> a place where moſt of thoſe deſignes have been hatched, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mixt in their intoreſts, and divided among themſelves, who have been ridden by all parties, but now of late more abuſed, and ingaged by the Scots Commiſſioners, and ſome others: You are full of diſcontents againſt this Parliament and Army, you were like to have begun a bloody war of late; had not ſome men, more wiſe and honeſt then others prevented it, you had inconſiderately,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116927:10"/> made way for your utter Ruine; and yet you think it now your happineſſe you live in Peace. Have you yet ſo many Bags to ſpare, as to invite your Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> in? Are your Cheſts ſo full that you know not how to imploy the overplus? let bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ireland</hi> have the benefit of your ſuperabundance: if ever ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther War ſhould be, you muſt launch out otherwiſe then ever you have done yet; you may not expect the Biſhops Lands, or Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents Eſtates to be ſold for your ſecurity, the Cavaliers will ſoon puniſh that which they call Sacriledge, and redeem the Revenue of the Clergy again: you had need make much of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they may ſettle things ſo, as they may perform their ingagements to you, and you may injoy what you lent your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for; the next party may quickly undoe what is now done: you have paid money only by way of Loan now, for which you have got well, the next turn you muſt give, and pay for lending alſo; what you have done for this Parliament againſt the Kings party, if ever the King get his power, you muſt do for him with an addition, and loſe your former profits too. Oh that you would now be wiſe! ſit down and eat the fat, and drink the ſweet of your injoyments under this Parliament, and let not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Kingdom come and make you Tributaries to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; Loſe not all the glory of your former Actions in a new ſtrain of Malignity? If any of you be ſtill diſcontented, and would gladly ſee a new overture of Affaires in relation to a War, I could only wiſh thoſe mens perſons were as far diſtant from the publick as their intereſts are, and then let them take their fill of War. Let every man conſider that there can be no pretence for War ſo ſtrong, and neceſſary, as the ſetling of our Lawes and Liberties (after Conqueſt of our common Enemy) can be for Peace. And of all men, the Citizens had need be quiet, and ſtick faſt to the Parliament, who injoy all they have by them; their trade is now coming in apace, their ſhops full, and except they long for to be plundred, and to lay temptations before their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116927:10"/> old Enemies, they cannot but deteſt any thought of a new ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or of countenancing ſuch an undertaking: yet doubtleſſe the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners have not courted them all this while for nothing, they have obſerved their tempers, caſt in Baits to trie their affections, and have no ſmall confidence in their aſſiſtance: But I hope they have obſerved and read the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners by this time, as well as they have formerly done them: if they will ſtill be made pack horſes to the <hi>Scots</hi> deſignes, I ſhall wiſh them no worſe maſters.</p>
            <p>I have one word to another party, of which I am ſorry to hear that they ſhould be thought a party diſtinct from the whole, the Levellers (falſely ſo called) and as innocently miſled, in whom the principles of liberty would ſhine very reſplendently, were they not mixed with ſome other unſuitable paſſions. You honeſt hearts, whoſe deſigne do you drive on with ſuch violence? are there not parties enough already, make no more, leſt you part your Intereſt from the Publique. Liberty is the garland we muſt weare after victory; but we muſt take heed how we proſecute the attainment of it; all things cannot be done at once, every man is not to be judge of his own liberty; there may be more dangers ſometimes in ſetling liberty, then in acting a warre. I fear you have done more diſſervice, and made more breaches in the honeſt Party, then the liberty of your particular perſons will countervaile, <hi>Avide ruendo ad libertatem, in ſervitutem delapſi ſunt,</hi> was an obſervation found out by old experience. It is obſerved in you, that the violence of your ſpirit hath ſprung from ſome particular diſcontents, and injuries received from particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which is an ill foundation; and honeſt men ſee not theſe holy, and Chriſtian-like gallantryes in your carriages, but much of ſelfe, and particular reflexions on private perſons; Oh let not advantages be given by you to your and our enemies againe, revenge not your particular quarrels to ſome members of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with opening a gap for the old Incendiaries to creep in at
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116927:11"/> to deſtroy us all. Ballance former ſervices with preſent failings, conſider the many exigencies men of publique imployment are put unto; they bear with your paſſions, you muſt with their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infirmities; wait but a while, and calmly indeavour in your places what you aim at, but let not your particular ſpirits ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage ſuch a publique work; and eſpecially remember who threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens to take advantage by our diviſions. I can aſſure, you give the Cavaliers ſuch a glimpſe of hope, that they as men riſen from the dead, at the hearing of your new agreements of the people, and ſuch like tranſactions: for while you ſeem to agree in that, you divide from the whole, and incourage the preſent deſigne to deſtroy our Union and Communion together. But I know the thoughts of a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Invaſion will ſettle your preſent thoughts to indeavour the ſtrengthening the preſent honeſt Party, under what names ſoever.</p>
            <p>What remaines, but that all honeſt and true-hearted <hi>Engliſh</hi> men ſhould unite their apprehenſions and affections in ſtanding for the particular Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> and the ſticking to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament; for though things have not been carried ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formely, as could have been wiſhed, and many members have had their particular failings, yet that is the moſt certaine remedy we have ever found; and if we vilifie, and undervalue them, we ſhake the foundations of our own peace, and there is no other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible remedy left us, to ſupport our ſelves, but what is violent, and unnaturall; and though private men may ſee many failings in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular actions, they muſt remember, that they cannot ſee all the difficulties they meet with, nor all the ſecret principles and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they act by; and that what ever paſſeth through the beſt of men will need refining, and long continuance in variety of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires cannot but alter thoughts, and apprehenſions, if not princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. We now know the worſt of this Parliament, but we know not what will be the next; they are now going on happily, if we diſcourage them by our diviſions, the blame muſt lie on us,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116927:11"/> not on them, who cannot poſſible pleaſe all parties, in every cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of their deſires; and it is a mercy they have kept to the foundation of our liberties, and have not given it up yet, either to the King, or <hi>Scots;</hi> and their laſt declaration in Anſwer to the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners papers may ſatisfie the whole world in their abſolute intireneſſe to the Intereſt of this Kingdome, and may calme our ſpirits from ſuch murmurings as ariſe againſt them. I am ſorry to heare honeſt men ſo hot, to deſire a diſſolution of this Parliament, before we are freed of our feares, and they have ſetled the Kingdome in a poſitive defence againſt our enemies. It is better truſt them whom we know, and who promiſe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, then leave all to the hazard of a next Parliament, of whom we know nothing, nor how they may be packt, and how in the intervall deſignes may act. Let the laſt malignant electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Scotland</hi> for ever ſtand a Patterne to us, elſe we ſhall be wiſe when we have paid more for it.</p>
            <p>And that we may yet prevent this deſigne from the North, let us reflect on our former actings, and recall our firſt principles of ingagement in this warre. We may very well remember that the old Character which was given to our common Enemie, by which we diſtinguiſhed them, was from their owning the Kings Prerogative intereſt againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and the libertie of the Subject, from whence they were called Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants; and who ever owne the ſame intereſt, or ſeeke to ſet up the King in his Throne, contrary to the Propoſitions of Peace pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by both Houſes of Parliament, and do joyne with the ſame partie, cannot be looked upon any other notion, then as the common Enemie, though under another name; &amp; all honeſt men are to unite againſt them, as at firſt, except we mean to forſake our principles, or do imagine that our Enemies are regenerated, and that the King is turned purely for the libertie of the Subjects, and the Priviledges of Parliament, <hi>Cujus contrarium verum eſt,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116927:12"/> they had never more wicked intentions then now they have, nor their hearts fuller fraught with malice then at this day. But its our miſery, that we can ſee nothing but what we feele, nor will beleeve nothing before its too late to prevent it; we have not ſo much wit, that the ſame deſigne can be carried on by ſeverall mediums which ſeeme contrary to it. But if men will be ſecure, let them be undone by the danger. I hope wiſe men will take care for themſelves. If God will yet puniſh us with a ſenſeleſſe ſlaviſh ſpirit, its but the fruit of our own doings. Its happy for honeſt men they have a reſerve at laſt, but its ſad to thinke that ſo many gallant ſpirits in this juncture of time are divided, when diviſion is the greateſt prejudice to our affaires. Its no wonder that <hi>Englands</hi> glory and happineſſe hath beene the object of ſo much envie, and other Nations have ſuch ambitious eyes upon it; but the wonder is, that we ſhould by our own folly proſtrate ſo faire a Virgin to the raviſhments of everie ones luſt. We can exchange nothing with other Nations of our Liberties and Priviledges, without indangering their affections to it. It hath beene but a little part of our wiſdome, that we have given <hi>Scotland</hi> ſuch a ſair proſpect of our happineſs, we might have kept our ſecrets, and have beene kinde enough unto them too. But we cannot now help it, you ſee what a vertue men make of neceſſitie, let us be wiſe for time to come, and know that a faire and loving diſtance from <hi>Scotland</hi> will not at all prejudice our condition, ſo long as we keep to the ſubſtance of our union, &amp; correſpondence in mutual affaires; any neereneſſe beſides will but make them covet, and us fear. It ſtands upon you to have your eyes in your head, and to obſerve where you are, and what you are comming unto, and if all will not make you wiſe, there muſt be a whip provided for the back of ſuch fooles. It may be this diſcourſe may ſeeme needleſſe, and be thought only the frenzie of ſome melancholy ſpirit. I wiſh it may prove ſo, I ſhall be glad to loſe my paines, ſo they may loſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116927:12"/> their deſigns. It wil be my happineſs to be miſtaken in this, though timely caution never yet hindered any ſerious work. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with my heartie deſires to God, that he would open the eyes of this Nation, defeate the plots of our Enemies, ſettle us in Truth and Peace, and that while we are of one Nation, we may have one Intereſt in all publique Affairs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
